So, we're going to talk today about binary search trees.
我们今天将讨论二叉搜索树
It's something called randomly built binary search trees.
也就是我们所说的随机二叉搜索树
And, I'll abbreviate binary search trees
在这堂课里  我会——
as BST's throughout the lecture.
把二叉搜索树简称为BST
And, you of all seen binary search trees in one place or another,
其实你们都已经接触过二叉搜索树了
in particular, recitation on Friday.
就譬如 在上周五的复习课程中
So, we're going to build up the basic ideas presented there,
我们先学习一下基本概念
and talk about how to randomize them,
然后讲一下如何随机化
and make them good.
和如何优化它们
So, you know that there are good binary search trees
大家都知道好的二叉搜索树是怎样的
which are relatively balanced, something like this.
要相对平衡的  像这种
The height is log n.
高度是log n
We called them balanced, and that's good.
我们说这种树是平衡的  这是种好的情况
Anything order log n will be fine.
复杂度是log n阶的算法都是不错的
In terms of searching, it will then cost order log n.
查询的时候 它只需要花费log n阶的时间
And, there are bad binary search trees
但也有一些不太好的二叉搜索树
which have really large height, possibly as big as n.
高度太大  甚至可能是n
So, this is good, and this is bad.
所以 这种是好的 这种是坏的
We'd sort of like to know,
我们想知道
we'd like to build binary search trees
如何去构造那种
in such a way that they are good all the time,
能一直保持是复杂度良好
or at least most of the time.
或是在大多数时间下保持良好
There are lots of ways to do this,
其实有很多种方法
and in the next couple of weeks, we will see four of them,
在接下来几周  我们就会见到4种
if you count the problem set, I believe.
翻翻习题册就能看到
Today, we are going to use randomization
今天  我们用随机化的方法
to make them balanced most of the time in a certain sense.
使得二叉树在大部分情况下都能保持平衡
And then, in your problem set,
然后 在习题册中
you will make that in a broader sense.
你们会做得更为深入一些
But, one way to motivate this topic,
进入这个课题之前
so I'm not going to define
我不准备再花时间
randomly built binary search trees for a little bit.
去定义随机二叉搜索树
One way to motivate the topic is
其实  这个课题
through sorting, our good friend.
是跟我们的好朋友 排序相关的
So, there's a natural way to sort n numbers
所以 二叉搜索树也可以很自然地
using binary search trees.
用来对n个数排序
So, if I give you an array, A,
比如这里有个数组A
how would you sort that array
你准备怎么用封装好的二叉树操作
using binary search tree operations as a black box?
对它进行来排序呢?
Build the binary search tree,
很简单  先为数组构造一个二叉树
and then traverse it in order. Exactly.
然后按中序遍历它
So, let's say we have some initial tree,
好  我们有棵初始树
which is empty, and then for each element of the array,
只是空树而已  然后我们把数组每一个数...
we insert it into the tree.
都插入到树中
That's what you meant by building the search tree.
这样就是构造二叉树的过程
So, we insert A[i] into the tree.
我们将A[i]插入到树中
This is the binary search tree insertion, standard insertion.
这是二叉树标准的插入操作
And then, we do an in order traversal,
然后  我们做一次中序遍历
which in the book is called in order tree walk.
书里叫做中根遍历
OK, you should know these algorithms are,
你们都应该知道这些算法
but just for very quick reminder,
但还是简单地回顾一下
tree insert basically searches for that element A[i]
进行插入操作时  首先应该在树中查找A[i]
until it finds the place where it should have been
直到找到它合适位置为止
if it was in the tree already,
前提是  A[i]已经在树中的话
and then adds a new leaf there to insert that value.
然后再在那位置加上新的叶结点来插入这个值
Tree walk recursively walks the left subtree,
树的遍历是先递归地遍历左子树,
then prints out the root,
然后打印根结点
and then recursively walks the right subtree.
再接着递归遍历右子树
And, by the binary search tree property,
根据二叉搜索树的特性
that will print the elements out in sorted order.
这些元素就会被按顺序打印出来
So, let's do a quick example
举个例子
because this turns out to be
这个算法跟我们
related to another sorting algorithm we've seen already.
之前学过的一个排序算法是有关的
So, while the example is probably pretty trivial,
虽然例子会很简单  但我们会发现
the connection is pretty surprising.
两个算法之间的关系还是挺微妙的
At least, it was to me the first time I taught this class.
我第一次上这门课时也是这么想的
So, my array is three, one, eight, two, six, seven, five.
那么 我的数组里有3,1,8,2,6,7,5
And, I'm going to visit these elements
然后 我要从左往右地
in order from left to right,
来访问这些元素
and just build a tree.
并建立二叉树
So, the first element I see is three.
第一个元素是3
So, I insert three into an empty tree.
我把3插入到树中
That requires no comparisons.
一开始不需要经过比较
Then I insert one. I see, is one bigger or less than three?
接着插入1 先看看1是小于3还是大于3?
It's smaller. So, I put it over here.
小于3 所以把它放这里
Then I insert eight.
然后我插入8
That's bigger than three, so it get's a new leaf over here.
比3要大 所以这里多了新的叶结点
Then I insert two.
接着插入2
That sits between one and three.
大小在1和3之间
And so, it would fall off this right child of one.
所以它要落入1的右子树
So, I add two there.
我把2加在这里
Six is bigger than three, and less than eight.
6比3大  比8要小
So, it goes here.  Seven is bigger than three,
把它搁这  7比3大
and less than eight, bigger than six.
比8小  比6大
So, it goes here, and five fits in between three and five,
所以它就来到这 然后5在3和5之间
three and six rather.
是3和6之间才对
And so, that's the binary search tree that again.
那么 一棵二叉搜索树完成了
Then I run an in order traversal,
接着我对它进行中序遍历
which will print one, two, three, five, six, seven, eight.
依次打印出1,2,3,5,6,7,8
OK, I can run I quickly in my head
在我脑子里很快就能跑完这个
because I've got a big stack.
因为我脑里有个大堆栈
I've got to be a little bit careful.
不过我得细心一点
Of course, you should check that
当然  你应该检查
they come out in sorted order:
这些排出来的数是否按顺序
one, two, three, five, six, seven, eight.
1,2,3,5,6,7,8
And, if you don't have a big stack, you can go and buy one.
如果你们脑子里没有这个栈 你们可以给自己买一个
That's always useful.
还是非常有用的
Memory costs are going up a bit these days, or going down.
最近内存条价格也变得有升有降的
They should be because of politics,
是由于政策原因什么的
but price-fixing, or whatever.
价格调整了 管他呢
So, the question is, what's the running time of the algorithm?
问题是  这个算法的时间复杂度是多少?
Here, this is one of those answers where it depends.
这里 我给出其中一个可能的答案
The parts that are easy to analyze are, well, initialization.
整个流程里  容易分析的有初始化部分
The in order tree walk, how long does that take?
还有就是中序遍历 这要花多少时间?
n, good. So, it's order n for the walk,
n  没错 遍历需要n阶的时间
and for the initialization, which is constant.
而初始化的话只需要常数时间
The question is, how long does it take me to do n tree inserts?
问题是  n次插入要花多少时间?
Anyone want to guess any kind of
谁来猜一猜
answer to that question,  other than it depends?
谁来回答问题  还是先观望下？
I've already stolen the thunder there.
我听到这边有人说了
Yeah?
[教授]什么?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
[学生]...
Big Omega of n log n, that's good.
[教授]Ω(n log n) 很好
It's at least n log n. Why?
[教授]至少要n log n的时间  为什么?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
[学生]...
Right. So, you gave two reasons.
对  你给出了两个原因
The first one is because of the decision tree lower bound.
一个是决策树的时间下界
That doesn't actually prove this.
但这其实并没有证明这个观点
You have to be a little bit careful.
你需要再细心地想想
This is a claim that it's omega n log n all the time.
从你的论据来看二叉树的复杂度总是Ω(n log n)
It's certainly omega n log n in the worst case.
那样的话 最坏情况当然也是Ω(n log n)
Every comparison-based sorting algorithm
对于任何基于比较的排序算法而言
is omega n log n in the worst case.
在最坏情况下都至少需要Ω(n log n)的时间
It's also n log n every single time,
而二叉树的每一次都是花n log n的时间
omega n log n because of the second reason you gave,
然而会出现Ω(n log n)的情况  是由于你的第二个条件
which is the best thing that could happen
也就是最优情况的出现
is we have a perfectly balanced tree.
一棵完全平衡的二叉树
So, this is the figure that I have drawn the most
这是我在黑板上画得最多的图了
on a blackboard in my life,
今天我又刷新纪录了
the perfect tree on 15 nodes, I guess.
15个结点的完全二叉树
So, if we're lucky, we have this.
运气好的话  我们就能得到这样的树
And if you add up all the depths of the nodes here,
如果你把所有结点的深度都加起来
which gives you the search tree cost
那就得到总的查询时间
in particular, these n over two nodes in the bottom, each have depth log n.
最底层的这n/2个结点  每个点的深度都是log n
And, therefore, you're going to
那么你的操作
have to pay it least n log n for those.
就要花上至少n log n的时间
And, if you're less balanced, it's going to be even worse.
但是 如果树越不平衡 情况就会越差
That takes some proving, but it's true.
这点需要证明  但确实如此
So, it's actually omega n log n all the time.
这样的话  它确实总是Ω(n log n)的
OK, there are some cases, like you do know that
当然  如果你用的是一些别的算法
the elements are almost already in order,
而你又已经知道这些元素是有序的
you can do it in linear number comparisons.
你可以用线性时间来做一次比较
But here, you can't.
但你用二叉树就不行
Any other guesses at an answer to this question?
还有人有别的答案吗?
Yeah?
[教授]嗯嗯?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
[学生]...
Big O n^2? Good, why?
[教授]O(n^2)?  很好 为什么?
Right. We are doing n things,
[教授]对  我们进行n次操作
and each node has depth, at most, n.
而每个结点的深度都达到最大值n
So, the number of comparisons we're making per element we insert,
那么  我们每插入一个数所做的比较次数
is, at most, n. So that's, at most, n^2.
就是最大值n  换句话说  总共最大为n^2
Any other answers?
还有别的答案吗?
Is it possible for this algorithm to take n^2 time?
这个算法真的会比较n^2次吗?
Are there instances where it takes theta n^2?
有没例子可以说明它得到Θ(n^2)?
If it's already sorted, that would be pretty bad.
如果数组已经有序的话,这种情况很差
So, if it's already sorted
那么,假设它已经是有序的
or if it's reverse sorted, you are in bad shape
不管顺序逆序  这时树的形状都很差
because then you get a tree like this.
树的形状会是这样子的
This is the sorted case. And, you compute.
在有序的情况下  你们算算
So, the total cost, the time in general is going to be
总的花费时间应该是
the sum of the depths of the nodes for each node, X, in the tree.
树中每个结点X的深度的总和
And in this case, it's one plus two plus three plus four,
在这里 它就是1+2+3+4
this arithmetic series.
等差级数
There's n of them, so this is theta n squared.
有n个点 那么这里就是n的平方
It's like n^2 over two.
准确点是n的平方除以二
So, that's bad news.
这是条坏消息
The worst-case running time of this algorithm is n^2.
最坏情况下算法的时间复杂度为n^2
Does that sound familiar at all,
是不是有点似曾相识？
and algorithms worst-case running time is n^2,
算法最坏情况的时间复杂度为n^2
in particular, in the already-sorted case?
特别是 处理有序元素的情况？
But if we're lucky, at the lucky case,
但是  运气好的话
as we said, it's a balanced tree.
我们得到的是一棵平衡树
Wouldn't that be great?
很不错吧？
Anything with omega log n height would give us
只要树的高度是Ω(log n)的话
a sorting algorithm that runs in n log n.
我们的排序算法跑起来就只用n log n
So, in the lucky case, we are n log n.
所以 在最好的情况下 我们只要花n log n的时间
But in the unlucky case, we are n^2
而最坏的情况下就是n^2
and unlucky case is sorted.
最坏情况就是碰到有序元素
Does it remind you of any algorithm we've seen before?
有没有联想到以前见过的某种算法?
Quicksort.
快速排序
It turns out the running time of this algorithm
其实二叉树算法运行时间
is the same as the running time of quicksort
跟快排的运行时间是一样的
in a very strong sense.
非常的相似
It turns out the comparisons that this algorithm makes
事实上  二叉树里用的比较方法
are exactly the same comparisons that quicksort makes.
和快排里用的比较方法是完全一样的
It makes them in a different order,
虽然它们比较的的顺序不一样
but it's really the same algorithm in disguise.
但实际上它们是失散多年的亲兄弟
That's the surprise here.
算法世界真奇妙
So, in particular, we've already analyzed quicksort.
既然我们已经分析过快速排序算法
We should get something for free out of that analysis.
那我们就要把分析的结果消化为自己的知识
So, the relation is, BST sort
BST排序跟快排的关系就是
and quicksort make the same comparisons
它们其实做的是相同的比较
but in a different order.
只是比较的顺序不一样
So, let me walk through the same example we did before:
让我用之前的例子给大家回顾一遍:
three, one, eight, two, six, seven, five.
3,1,8,2,6,7,5
So, there is an array.
这个是数组
We are going to run a particular version of quicksort.
我们跑一下快速排序特别版
I have to be a little bit careful here.
这里要注意
It's sort of the obvious version of quicksort.
快排的版本有很多
Remember, our standard, boring quicksort is
记得我们最标准、最老套的快排
you take the first element as the partition element.
它是选取第一个元素来作为划分元素的
So, I'll take three here.
这里我选3
And, I split into the elements less than three,
先分出小于3的元素
which is one and two.
有1和2
And, the elements bigger than three,
其他的是大于3的
which is eight, six, seven, five.
有8,6,7,5
And, in this version of quicksort,
在这个版本的快排中
I don't change the order of the elements, eight, six, seven, five.
我先不改变元素的顺序 8 6 7 5
So, let's say the order is preserved
先保持这些元素之间的顺序
because only then will this equivalence hold.
因为只有这样做才符合上面的性质
So, this is sort of a stable partition algorithm.
这个是划分算法是稳定的
It's easy enough to do. It's a particular version of quicksort.
算法很简单  是典型的快速排序
And soon, we're going to randomize it.
之后我们要将它随机化
And after we randomize, this difference doesn't matter.
随机化之后  这些区别的影响就不重要了
OK, then on the left recursion,
好的 在左边这个递归部分里
we split in the partition element.
我们再用划分元素来分割
There is things less than one,
这边是小于1的元素
which is nothing, things bigger than one,  which is two.
也就是空集  这边是大于1的  只有2
And then, that's our partition element.
然后 这又是新的划分元素
We are done. Over here, we partition on eight.
左边的做完了  再用8来做右边的划分
Everything is less than eight.
所有数都比8小
So, we get six, seven, five, nothing on the right.
那么 左边有6 7 5  右边为空
Then we partition at six.
然后再用6来划分
We get things less than six, mainly five,
得出比6小的数  只有5
things bigger than six, mainly seven.
比6大的 只有7
And, those are sort of partition elements in a trivial way.
这就是用很普通的方法划分出来的元素
Now, this tree that we get on the partition elements
现在,通过划分元素得出的这棵树
looks an awful lot like this tree.
跟这棵树非常相像
OK, it should be exactly the same tree.
好吧  它们完全就是同一棵树
And, you can walk through,
你们自己再回想下
what comparisons does quicksort make?
快排做了哪些比较?
Well, first, it compares everything to three,
一开始  3被用来跟所有数比较
OK, except three itself.
当然  除了3自身外
Now, if you look over here,
现在你看这边
what happens when we are inserting elements?
我们插入元素的时候发生了什么?
Well, each time we insert an element,
每次插入新元素时
the first thing we do is compare with three.
所做的第一件事就是与3比较
If it's less than, we go to the left branch.
如果是小于 我们就走左分支
If it's greater than, we go to the right branch.
如果是大于 我们就走右分支
So, we are making all these comparisons with three in both cases.
在两种方法里我们都拿3跟所有数比较
Then, if we have an element less than three,
然后 如果有比3小的数
it's either one or two.
就是1或2
If it's one, we're done. No comparisons happen here one to one.
如果是1 结束  1和1之间不用比较
But, we compare two to one.
我们比较的是2和1
And indeed, when we insert two over there
实际上 当我们将2插入到这里时
after comparing it to three, we compare it to one.
它跟3比较完之后  再跟1比较
And then we figure out that it happens here.
这时 我们会发现这里所做的操作
Same thing happens in quicksort.
跟快速排序是一样的
For elements greater than three,
对于大于3的元素
we compare everyone to eight here
我们全都拿去跟8比较
because we are partitioning with respect to eight,
因为在快排这里 我们是用8来划分的
and here because that's the next node after three.
而在二叉树这里 8则是3的下一个结点
As soon as eight is inserted, we compare everything
所以在插入8之后  后面的数
with eight to see in fact that's less than eight, and so on:
都要跟8比较  即使它们都比8要小
so, all of the same comparisons, just in a different order.
所以 我们都在做相同的比较 只是比较的顺序不同
So, this has various consequences in the analysis.
通过分析我们能得到一些推论
So, in particular, the worst-case running time is theta n^2,
而其中一个  在最坏情况下 它的时间复杂度为Θ(n^2)
which is not so exciting.
并不是那么给力
What we really care about is the randomized version
所以 我们真正关心的是随机化版本
because that's what performs well.
因为它的运行效率很不错
So, randomized BST sort is just like randomized quicksort.
随机化的BST排序就跟随机化的快排一样
So, the first thing you do is
所以你要做的第一件事就是
randomly permute the array uniformly,
随机、均匀地打乱数组的序列
picking all permutations with equal probability.
使得任意排列都有同样的概率出现
And then, we call BST sort.
然后 我们再调用BST排序
OK, this is basically
好的 这个基本上
what randomized quicksort could be formulated as.
也就是随机化快速排序算法的大体结构
And then, randomized BST sort is going to make
在这之后  随机化的BST排序
exactly the same comparisons as randomized quicksort.
和随机化的快排做的就是相同的比较了
Here, we are picking the root essentially randomly.
这里 我们主要是要随机选出一个根结点
And here in quicksort,
而在快速排序里的话
you are picking the partition elements randomly.
就是要随机地选出一个划分元素
It's the same difference.
就是同样的算法
OK, so the time of this algorithm
所以这个算法的时间复杂度
equals the time of randomized quicksort
跟随机化快排的时间复杂度是一样的
because we are making the same comparisons.
因为我们做的都是一样的比较
So, the number of comparisons is equal.
比较的次数是一样的
And this is true as random variables.
这是因为
The random variable, the running time,
它的随机变量 运行时间
this algorithm is equal to the random variable of this algorithm.
跟快速排序都是同样的
In particular, the expectations are the same.
两种算法花费期望时间的都是相等的
OK, and we know that the expected running time
对于n个元素的随机化快速排序
of randomized quicksort on n elements is?
我们都应该知道它的期望运行时间是多少吧?
Oh boy. n log n. Good. I was a little worried there.
骚年啊  是n log n  还好 刚刚我都不淡定了
OK, so in particular,
好的 同样地
the expected running time of BST sort is n log n.
BST排序的期望运行时间也是n log n
Obviously, this is not too exciting from a sorting point of view.
显然 从排序层面上看这结论也没什么
Sorting was just sort of to see this connection.
排序只是为了研究两个算法的关系
What we actually care about,
我们真正关心的是
and the reason I've introduced this BST sort
也是我给你们介绍BST排序的原因
is what the tree looks like.
就是为了研究树的形状
What we really want is that search tree.
我们想要的是这棵搜索树
The search tree can do more than sort. n order traversals
搜索树能做的不仅仅是排序和n阶的遍历
are a pretty boring thing to do with the search tree.
这对于搜索树而言只是一个普通的应用
You can search in a search tree.
你可以在搜索树里进行查找
So, OK, that's still not so exciting.
好吧 这也是没什么大不了的
You could sort the elements
因为你也能够先将元素排序
and then put them in an array and do binary search.
然后再把元素放回数组中做二分查找
But, the point of binary search trees,
但是 二叉搜索树的重点
instead of binary search arrays,
它和普通有序数组所不一样的地方
is that you can update them dynamically.
就是你能更新树里的元素
We won't be updating them dynamically in this lecture,
这堂课里我不讲动态的更新操作
and we will in Wednesday and on your problem set.
星期三会讲 习题册里也有
For now, it's just sort of warm-up.
现在只是预习一下
Let's say that the elements aren't changing.
假设说这些元素都是不变的
We are building one tree from the beginning.
我们重新建立一棵树
We have all n elements ahead of time.
之前说了有n个元素
We are going to build it randomly.
然后我们随机地建立一棵树
We randomly permute that array.
先将数组随机打乱
Then we throw all the elements into a binary search tree.
接着将全部元素都加到二叉搜索树中
That's what BST sort does. Then it calls n order traversal.
这个是BST排序的过程  然后再遍历一次
I don't really care about n order traversal.
我并不关心这个遍历本身
What I want, because we've just analyzed it.
我只是想通过遍历来分析
It would be a short lecture if I were done.
我应该很快能讲完
What we want is this randomly built BST,
我们想研究的是这棵随机化的二叉树
which is what we get out of this algorithm.
用这个算法求得的二叉树
So, this is the tree resulting from randomized BST sort,
因此 这个就是用随机化BST排序得到的结果树
OK, resulting from randomly permute in the array
好的  先把数组排列随机化
of just inserting those elements
再把这个数组的元素...
using the simple tree insert algorithm.
用简单的算法 插入到树里 就是我们要的结果
The question is, what does that tree look like?
问题是,这棵树是什么样子的
And in particular, is there anything
更重要的是 我们又能从这其中
we can conclude out of this fact?
得出什么结论来?
The expected running time of BST sort is n log n.
BST排序的期望运行时间为n log n
OK, I've mentioned cursorily
嗯  我好几次粗略地
what the running time of BST sort is, several times.
提到过BST排序的运行时间
It was the sum. So, this is the time of BST sort on n elements.
它是深度的和  嗯...这个是n个元素的BST排序时间
It's the sum over all nodes, X, of the depth of that node.
它是所有结点的深度的和  X是某个结点的深度
OK, depth starts at zero
好的,深度是从0开始算的
and works its way down because the root element,
然后越往下深度越大 因为在插入根结点时
you don't make any comparisons
你不用做任何比较
beyond that, you are making whatever the depth is comparisons.
但之后 你每往深处走一步都要做比较
OK, so we know that this thing is,
所以 我们知道BST的排序时间
in expectation we know that this is n log n.
它的期望大小为n log n
What does that tell us about the tree?
这点跟树有什么关系?
This is for all nodes, X, in the tree.
这对于树里的任意结点X来说
Does it tell us anything about
它是否就告诉我们
the height of the tree, for example? Yeah?
比如说  树的高度是多少  嗯嗯?
STUDENT: [INAUDIBLE]
[学生]...
Right, intuitively,
[教授]对  直观的角度来讲
it says that the height of the tree is theta log n,
它说明树的高度是Θ(logn)
and not n. But, in fact, it doesn't show that.
而不是n  但实际上 它并没有表现这一点
And that's why if you feel that that's just intuition,
这就是为什么这只是从直观的角度来讲
but it may not be quite right. Indeed it's not.
它可能有问题  而实际上 它确实错了
Let me tell you what it does say.
我来告诉你们正确的结论
So, if we take expectation of both sides, here we get n log n.
如果我们对等式两边求期望值  这里是n log n
So, the expected value of that is n log n.
这边的期望值是n log n
So, over here, well, we get the expected total depth,
而另一边  我们得到的是总深度的期望值
which is not so exciting.
也没什么特别
Let's look at the expected average depth.
我们再看看平均深度的期望值
So, if I look at one over n,
如果我用1/n
the sum over all n nodes in the tree of the depth of X,
乘以树所有结点X的深度之和
that would be the average depth over all the nodes.
就得出所有结点深度的平均值
And what I should get is theta n log n over n
我应该得到Θ(n log n)/n
because I divided n on both sides.
因为我两边都除以n了
And, I'm using, here, linearity of expectation, which is log n.
然后根据期望的线性性质  算出log n
So, what this fact about the expected running time
所以这个运行时间的期望值告诉我
tells me is that the average depth in the tree is log n,
树结点的平均深度为log n
which is not quite the height of the tree being log n.
并不相当于说树的高度就是log n
OK, remember the height of the tree
你们要记住树的高度
is the maximum depth of any node.
是指所有结点中的最大深度
Here, we are just bounding the average depth.
这里我们只是估计平均深度的范围
Let's look at an example of a tree.
我们来看一个例子
I'll draw my favorite picture.
平衡树神马的最喜欢画了
So, here we have a nice balanced tree,
现在我们有一棵还算漂亮的平衡树
let's say, on half of the nodes or a little more.
应该说  起码有一半以上的节点都还分布得不错
And then, I have one really long path
但在其中某个结点下面
hanging off one particular leaf.
伸出了一条很长的树径
It doesn't matter which one.
是哪个点并不重要
And, I'm going to say that this path has length,
这条路径的长度呢
with a total height here, I want to make root n,
就是树的总高度   我假设它为根号n
which is a lot bigger than log n.
要比log n大很多
This is roughly log n.
这边的高度差不多是log n
It's going to be log of n minus root n, or so, roughly.
大约是log(n-√n)
So, most of the nodes have logarithmic height and,
大多数结点有着对数级的高度
sorry, logarithmic depth.
错了,是对数级的深度
If you compute the average depth in this particular tree,
如果你算算这颗树的平均深度
for most of the nodes, let's say it's,
对于大多数结点而言
at most, n of the nodes have height log n.
最多的话 有n个结点的深度为log n
And then, there are root n nodes, at most,
然后这边最多有根号n个结点
down here, which have depth, at most, root n.
一直下来  最大深度为根号n
So, it's, at most, root n times root n.
所以最多有根号n乘以根号n
In fact, it's like half that, but not a big deal.
实际上只有一半那么多  不过影响不大
So, this is n. So, this is n log n, or, sorry,
所以这里是n 这里是n log n  嗯不好意思
average depth...I have to divide everything by n.
因为是平均深度 所以全部都要除以n
n log n would be rather large for an average height, average depth.
n log n 作为平均深度就太大了
So, the average depth here is log n,
所以这里的平均深度为log n
but the height of the tree is square root of n.
但树的高度是根号n
So, this is not enough.
说明刚刚的结论是不充分的
Just to know that the average depth is log n
只知道平均深度为log n的话
doesn't mean that the height is log n.
并不代表树的高度就是log n
OK, but the claim is this theorem for today
好的 但今天要证明一个定理
is that the expected height of
那就是一颗随机化的二叉搜索树
a randomly built binary search tree is indeed log n.
它的高度的期望值确实是log n
BST is order log n.
BST是log n阶的
This is what we like to know because that tells us,
这就是我们想研究的内容  因为这说明
if we just build a binary search tree randomly,
只要我们建立随机化二叉搜索树
then we can search in it in log n time.
我们就能实现log n的查询时间
OK, for sorting, it's not as big a deal.
好吧 对于排序的话就没那么重要
We just care about the expected running time of creating the thing.
因为那样我们只关心建立树的运行时间
Here, now we know that once we prove this theorem,
但这里  现在我们知道一旦我们证明这定理
we know that we can search quickly in expectation,
我们就能够快速地查询
in fact, most of the time.
而且是在大多数情况下都可以
So, the rest of today's lecture will be proving this theorem.
今天这堂课剩下的时间就是要证明这个定理
It's quite tricky, as you might imagine.
有一点技巧 正如你所想的那样
It's another big probability analysis
是另一个大型的概率分析
along the lines of quicksort and everything.
涉及到快排等等的一切
So, I'm going to start with an outline of the proof,
所以我准备先列出证明过程的纲领
unless there are any questions about the theorem.
除非对定理本身有问题
It should be pretty clear what we want to prove.
否则 我们要证明的目标应该是很明确的
This is even weirder than most of the analyses we've seen.
这个证明比我们之前见过的所有分析都要奇怪
It's going to use a fancy trick,
会用到一个很有趣的技巧
which is exponentiating a random variable.
对一个随机变量取幂
And to do that we need a tool called Jenson's inequality.
还要用到一个工具就是Jenson不等式
We are going to prove that tool.
先证明这个不等式吧
Usually, we don't prove probability tools.
通常来说我们不去证明概率学工具
But this one we are going to prove.
但这个我们还是去证明一次
It's not too hard. It's also basic analysis.
不是很难 也是一些基本的分析
So, the lemma, says that if we have
那么 有个引理指出 如果我们..
what's called to a convex function, f,
有一个凹函数f
and you should all know what that means,
你们应该都知道这个是什么
but I'll define it soon in case you have forgotten.
忘了的话我等下会再定义一次
If you have a convex function, f,
假设你有个凹函数f
and you have a random variable, X,
还有个随机变量X
you take f of the expectation.
用X的期望值代入f中
That's, at most, the expectation of f of that random variable.
得到的最大值不会超过f(X)的期望值
Think about it enough and draw a convex function
自己想一想 画个凹函数看看
that is fairly intuitive, I guess.
我觉得这个是相当直观的
But we will prove it.
但我们会证明它的
What that allows us to do is instead of
我们能做的
analyzing the random variable that tells us the height of a tree,
并不是直接分析用来代表树高度的随机变量
so, X_n I'll call the random variable, RV,
X_n用来表示随机化的...
of the height of a BST, randomly constructed BST
BST的高度 我们要分析的
on n nodes we will analyze.
是n个节点的随机化的BST
Well, instead of analyzing this desired random variable, X_n,
好的 我们分析的并不是这个随机变量X_n
sorry, this should have been in capital X.
不好意思  这应该是大写的X
We can analyze any convex function of X_n.
我们转而分析关于X_n的任意凹函数
And, we're going to analyze the exponentiation.
而且 我们准备分析的是取幂函数
So, I'm going to define Y_n to be two to the power of X_n.
那么 我定义Y_n为2的X_n次方
OK, the big question here is why bother doing this?
问题是为什么要这么做?
The answer is because it works
原因是这么做很有用
and it wouldn't work if we analyze X_n.
而且我们只分析X_n的话是没用的
We will see some intuition of that later on,
我们待会儿再直观地看一下
but it's not very intuitive.
其实也并不是很直观
This is our analysis where you need this extra trick.
在这个分析里你就要用到特别的技巧
So, we're going to bound the expectation of Y_n,
我们先要算Y_n期望值的上下界
and from that, and using Jensen's inequality,
再在那个基础上运用Jensen不等式
we're going to get a bound on the expectation of X_n,
来求出X_n的期望值的界限
a pretty tight bound, actually,
实际上 它的界限相当的紧凑
because if we can bound the exponent up to constant factors,
这样做是因为 如果能给指数函数找到常数界限
the exponentiation up to constant factors,
也就是给取幂结果找到常数界限
we can bound X_n even better
那我们就能更方便地算出X_n的界限
because you take logs to get X_n.
因为那时只要取Y_n对数就得到X_n
So, we will even figure out what the constant is.
我们甚至能找出这个常数是多少
So, what we will prove, this is the heart of the proof,
那么,我们将要证明的重点
is that the expected value of Y_n is order n^3.
就是Y_n的期望值是n^3阶的
Here, we won't really know what the constant is.
这里我们没法知道这个常数多大
We don't need to.
也不需要知道
And then, we put these pieces together.
最后再来做总结
So, let's do that.
开始证明吧
What we really care about is the expectation of X_n,
我们真正关心的是X_n的期望
which is the height of our tree.
也就是我们的树的高度
What we find out about is this fact.
我们要证明的是这条式子
So, leave some horizontal space here.
呃,这里留一点空间
We get the expectation of two to the X_n.
我们要求出2的X_n次方的期望值
That's the expectation of Y_n.
也就是Y_n的期望值
So, we learned that that's order n^3.
假设我们知道这个是n^3阶的
And, Jensen's inequality tells us that
那么 Jensen不等式告诉我们,
if we take this function, two to the X,
如果我们把这个函数2的X次方
we plug it in here, that on the left-hand side
把它放这里  那么在等号的左边
we get two to the E of X.
我们就有2的E(X)次方
So, we get two to the E of X_n is at most E of two to the X_n.
那么 我们就得出2^E(X_n) 最大不超过 2^X_n的期望
So, that's where we use Jensen's inequality,
这就是我们用到Jensen不等式的地方
because what we care about is E of X_n.
因为我们关心的是X_n的期望值
So now, we have a bound.
现在 因为我们有了它的范围了
We say, well, two to the E of X_n is, at most, n^3.
我们现在发现2^E(X_n) 最大为n^3
So, if we take the log of both sides,
然后只要两边同时取对数
we get E of X_n is, at most, the log of n^3.
就能得出X_n的期望不超过log(n^3)
OK, I will write it in this funny way, log of order n^3,
嗯  我把它写得有趣点 log(O(n^3))
which will actually tell us the constant.
这就样我们就知道那个常数是多少了
This is three log n plus order one.
它等于3 log n加上O(1)
So, we will prove that the expected
所以我们就证明了
height of a randomly constructed binary search tree
一个n结点的随机化二叉树的期望高度
on n nodes is roughly three log n, at most.
大约为3 log n
OK, I will say more about that later.
这个结果我待会儿会讲得更详细一点
So, you've now seen the end of the proof.
现在大家都知道证明到最后就是这样子
That's the foreshadowing.
这是给你们提前剧透下
And now, this is the top-down approach.
刚刚我们从上而下做了一次模拟
So, you sort of see what the steps are.
你们大概知道证明的步骤了
Now, we just have to do the steps.
现在 我们将要把这些步骤过一遍
OK, step one: take a bit of work, but it's easy
好的 第一步要花点工夫 不过很简单
because it's pretty basic stuff.
因为都是基础的东西
Step two is just a definition and we are done.
第二步只是一个定义而且我们已经完成了
Step three is probably the hardest part.
第三步应该算是最难的部分
Step four, we've already done.
第四步,我们已经证明完了
So, let's start with step one.
那我们从第一步开始
So, the first thing I need to do is define a convex function
第一件事就是去定义一个凹函数
because we are going to manipulate the definition a fair amount.
因为我们要多次运用到这个定义
So, this is a notion from real analysis.
这个是正式的分析里来的一个概念
Analysis is a fancy word for calculus
对于微积分来说分析是一个独特的词汇
if you haven't taken the proper analysis class.
如果你没上过那些数学分析的课的话
You should have seen convexity in any calculus class.
你们也应该在微积分课上见过函数的凹凸性
A convex function is one that looks like this.
凹函数是这个样子的
OK, good. One way to formalize that notion is
将这个概念写成公式就是
to consider any two points on this curve.
在弧上选取两个点
So, I'm only interested in functions from reals to reals.
我只关注实数函数
So, it looks like this. This is f of something.
所以 它看起来是这样子的 这个是f某某
And, this is the something.
这个是某某
If I take two points on this curve,
如果我从弧线上选取两点
and I draw a line segment connecting them,
画一条线段来连接它们
that line segment is always above the curve.
那么这条线段总是在弧线上的
That's the meaning of convexity.
这就是凹性
It has a geometric notion, which is basically the same.
它还有个几何上的概念 不过基本上是一样的
But for functions, this line segment should stay above the curve.
但对于函数而言 线段总是在弧上方
The line does not stay above the curve.
但直线并不在弧的上方
If I extended it farther, it goes beneath the curve, of course.
如果我把它延伸一下 它当然就在弧线下面了
But, that segment should.
但是这条线段应该在弧的上方
So, I'm going to formalize that a little bit.
我准备将这个定义公式化
I'll call this x, and then this is f of x.
我们设这个为x  那这就是f(x)
And, I'll call this y, and this is f of y.
这个为y  这就是f(y)
So, the claim is that I take any number between x and y,
而需要证明的 就是我在x y之间任意选一个点
and I look up, and I say, OK, here's the point on the curve.
当我往上面看 好的 弧上面有一个点
Here's the point on the line segment.
线段上也有一个点
The value of that point on the y value, here,
线段上的点的y坐标值  这里
should be greater than or equal to the y value here, OK?
应该大于或等于弧上的点的y坐标值  对吧?
To figure out what the point is,
要理解这个点的性质
we need some, I would call it geometry.
我们需要用到一些几何知识
I'm sure it's an analysis concept, too.
我敢保证它也是数学分析中的一个概念
But, I'm a geometer, so I get to call it geometry.
但我是研究几何的  所以我叫它几何学
If you have two points, p and q,
如果你有p q两点
and you want to parameterize this line segment between them,
而你想用参数来表示它们之间的线段
so, I want to parameterize some points here,
比如我想将这几个点参数化
the way to do it is to take a linear combination.
一个方法就是用线性组合
And, if you should have taken some linear algebra,
如果你们学过了线性代数的话
linear combination look something like this.
这种就叫线性组合
And, in fact, we're going to take something
而且我们实际上还用到
called an affine combination where alpha plus beta equals one.
一种叫做仿射组合的东西  α+β=1
It turns out, if you take all such points,
这表明  如果你把满足这条式的点都找出来
some number, alpha, times the point, p, plus some number,
任意取一个α值  乘以点p  加上
beta times the point, q, where alpha plus beta equals one.
任意β乘以点q  而且满足α+β=1
If you take all those points,
如果找出所有这样的点
you get the entire line here, which is nifty.
你会得到一整条漂亮的直线
But, we don't want the entire line.
但我们不想要一整条直线
If you also constrained alpha and beta to be nonnegative,
如果你同时限定α和β都是非负的话
you just get this line segment.
你就刚好得到一条线段
So, this forces alpha and beta to be between zero and one
那么α和β都只能在0和1之间取值
because they have to sum to one,
因为它们加起来要等于1
and they are nonnegative.
而且它俩都是非负的
So, what we are going to do here is
所以我们这里要做的是
take alpha times x plus beta times y.
用αx 加上 βy
That's going to be our point between with these constraints:
这些就是在x、y之间 符合我们条件的点
alpha plus beta equals one.
α+β=1
Alpha and beta are greater than or equal to zero.
α和β都大于0
Then, this point is f of that.
然后 这点是αx+βy的f值
This is f of alpha x plus beta, y.
这个是f(αx+βy)
And, this point is the linear interpolation
而这个点是在f(x)与f(y)之间的
between f of x and f of y, the same one.
线段上的一个插值 同样的
So, it's alpha times f of x plus beta times f of y.
它就是αf(x)+βf(y)
OK, that's the intuition.
好的,这个是直觉推论
If you didn't follow it, it's not too big a deal
如果有人没跟上的话  也没关系
because all we care about
因为我们关心的是
are the symbolic answer for proving things.
证明出来的符号化的答案
But, that's where this comes from.
但是答案就从这里来的
So, here's the definition.
那么 这里就是定义
Its function is convex.
我们定义凹函数为...
If, for all x and y, and all alpha and beta
对于任意x和y以及任意的α和β
are greater than or equal to zero, whose sum is one,
满足α、β≥0，α+β=1
we have f of alpha x plus beta y is less than
我们有f(αx+βy)是小于
or equal to alpha f of x plus beta f of y.
或等于αf(x)+βf(y)
So, that's just saying that this y coordinate here
也就是说在函数线上的y坐标是
is less than or equal to this y coordinate.
小于线段上的y坐标的
OK, but that's the symbolism behind that picture.
好的  这式子就是那个图的数学符号表示
OK, so now we want to prove Jensen's inequality.
那好 我们现在想证明Jensen不等式
OK, we're not quite there yet.
其实离证明完还差得远呢
We are going to prove a simple lemma,
我们先要证明一个引理
from which it will be easy to derive Jenson's equality.
有了它就容易推导出Jensen不等式
So, this is the theorem we are proving.
这就是我们要证明的定理
So, here's a lemma about convex functions.
那么 有个关于凹凸函数的引理
You may have seen it before.
你们之前可能见过了
It will be crucial to Jensen's inequality.
它对Jensen不等式至关重要
So, suppose, this is a statement
假设这个命题不仅适用于两点
about affine combinations of n things instead of two things.
而且适用于函数上的n个点的仿射组合
So, this will say that convexity
这么一来 函数的凹性就可以
can be generalized to taking n things.
推广至n个点
So, suppose we have n real numbers,
假设我们有n个实数
and we have n values alpha i, alpha one up to alpha n.
以及n个α值  从α_1到α_n
They are all nonnegative.
它们全都是非负的
And, their sum is one.
而且它们的和为1
So, the sum of alpha k, I guess,
我写成α_k的总和
k equals one to n, is one.
k从1到n  它们的总和是1
So, those are the assumptions.
那么,这些都是假定给出的条件
The conclusion is the same thing, but summing over all k.
结论是一致的 不过换成了k个值的总和
So, k equals one to n, alpha_k * x_k.
k从1到n  算出α_k * x_k的总和
Take f of that versus taking the sum of the alphas times the f's.
代入f中  再和α_k * f(x_k)的总和比较
k equals one to n.
k从1到n
So, the definition of convexity is exactly that statement,
由此发现  凹性的定义正跟刚刚的命题一致
but where n equals two.
只是刚刚那个是当n=2时
OK, alpha one and alpha two are alpha and beta.
是吧  α1和α2分别对应α和β
This is just a statement for general n.
这个是对于n个值的一般化的命题
And, you can interpret this in some funnier way,
你们也可以用更有趣的方法来解释这条式子
which I won't get into. Oh, sure, why not?
不过人家才不会这么做呢  骗你的 能不会吗?
I'm a geometer.
我可是几何学者
So, this is saying you take several points on this curve.
那么 比如你在弧线上选取若干个点
You take the polygon that they define.
你再从这些点中构成多边形
So, these are straight-line segments.
这些都是直线段
You take the interior.
你取中间部分
If you take an affine combination like that,
如果像那样运用仿射组合
you will get a point inside that polygon,
你就会在多边形中得到一点
or possibly on the boundary.
又或者在边上得到一点
The claim is that all those points are above the curve.
这说明这些点都是在弧线上方的
Again, intuitively: true if you draw a nice,
而且 直观上看就是真的 如果你画的是一个漂亮的
canonical convex curve,
正规的凹弧线的话
but in fact, it's true algebraically, too.
但事实上  在代数里也是对的
It's always a good thing.
这都是好事
Any suggestions on how we might prove this theorem, this lemma?
怎么证明这些定理、引理？ 有人有什么想法吗?
It's pretty easy. So, what technique might we use to prove it?
其实相当简单 那么 我们用什么技巧去证明它?
One word: induction.
一个词: 归纳法
Always a good answer, yeah.
一直好方法 从未被超越
Induction should shout out at you here
你应该大声喊出归纳法
because we already know that
因为我们都已经知道
this is true by definition of convexity for n equals two.
当n=2时 函数凹性定义为真
So, the base case is clear.
这样 基础命题解决了
In fact, there's an even simpler base case,
实际上 这还不算最基础的
which is when n equals one.
最基础是当n等于1时
If n equals one, then you have one number that sums to one.
如果n=1 那你仅有一个数而且和为1
So, alpha one is one. And so, nothing is going on here.
所以α1=1  那这里没有别的东西了
This is just saying that f of one times x_1 is,
这就是说f(1*x_1)
at most, one times f of x_1:
最大不超过1乘以f(x_1)
so, not terribly exciting because that holds with the equality.
也不是什么神奇的东西  因为这等式本身就是成立的
OK, so we don't even need the n equals two base case.
好的 我们甚至没用到n=2时的基础命题
So, the interesting part,
有趣的地方来了
although still not terribly interesting, is the induction step.
虽然不是特别有趣 其实就是归纳法
This is good practice in induction.
但这是数学归纳法的好应用
So, what we care about is this f of this linear combination,
那么 我们关心的是f的线性组合
f on combination,  alpha_k times x_k summed over all k.
对于所有k  α_k * x_k的总和代入f的值
Now, what I would like to do is apply induction.
现在要用到归纳法了
What I know about inductively, is say f of this sum,
我先从归纳中得知 这个和的f值
if it's summed only up to n minus one
假设已经知道它加到n-1的和
instead of all the way up to n.
而不是加到n的和
Any smaller sum I can deal with by induction.
比n小的情况都从归纳中解决了
So, I'm going to try and get rid of the nth term.
那么  我要尝试处理掉第n项
I want to separate it out.
我想将它分离出来
And, this is fairly natural
很自然就能写出来
if you've played with affine combinations before.
只要你之前用过仿射组合的话
But it's just some algebra.
就只是一些代数而已
So, I want to separate out the alpha_n*x_n term.
我想提出α_n * x_n这一项
And, I'd also like to make it an affine combination.
而且写成仿射组合的形式
This is the trick.
这就是个小技巧
Sorry, no f here.
不好意思 这里没f的
If I just removed the last term,
因为我把最后一项提出来了
the alpha k's from one up to n minus one
那这里就是α_k从1数到n-1
wouldn't sum to one anymore.
所以它们加起来就不等于1了
They'd sum to something smaller.
它们加起来要小于1
So, I can't just take out this term.
所以我不能简单地去掉这一项
I'm going to have to do some trickery here, x_k plus the f.
这里要到一点小技巧  这里是x_k..都在f里面
Good. So, you should see why this is true,
好的 你们要知道这条等式是成立的
because the one minus alpha n's cancel.
因为1-α_n能消掉后面的分母
And then, I'm just getting the sum of alpha_k*x_k,
消掉后  这边就剩下α_k * x_k的和
k equals one to n minus one, plus the alpha_n*x_n term.
k从1到n-1  再加上α_n * x_n项
So, I haven't done anything here.
所以这里啥都没动过
These are equal.
等号两边是相等的
But now, I have this nifty feature,
但现在我们却得到了个漂亮的特征
that on the one hand, these two numbers,
一方面 这两个数
alpha n and one minus alpha n sum to one.
α_n以及1-α_n加起来等于1
And on the other hand, if I did it right,
另一方面  如果我没错的话
these numbers should sum up to one
这些数加起来应该等于1
just going from one up to n minus one.
就是从1到n-1的和
Why do they sum up to one?
为什么它们的和为1?
Well, these numbers summed up to one minus alpha n.
分子全部加起来等于1-α_n
And so, I'm dividing everything by one minus alpha n.
然后这些加起来的和再除以1-αn
So, they will sum to one.
所以它们和仍然为1
So now, I have two affine combinations.
所以现在我有两个仿射组合
I just apply the two things that I know.
把两个已知条件都用上
I know this affine combination will work because, well, why?
我知道这里要用到仿射组合  为什么？
Why can I say that this is alpha n f of x_n
为什么这个等于α_n * f(x_n)
plus one minus alpha n f of this crazy sum?
加上1-α_n乘以这一大坨东西？
Shout it out. There are two possible answers.
大声说 我听到有两个答案
One is correct, and one is incorrect.
一个是对的  另一个是错的
So, which will it be?
会是哪个呢?
This should have been less than or equal to.
这个应该是小于等于号
That's important.
很重要的  别搞错
It's on the board. It can't be too difficult.
答案就写在黑板上  不可能太难
So, I'm treating this as just one big X value.
我现在把这整个当成一个大X
So, I have some x_n, and I have some crazy X.
这里有些x_n  还有个超大的X
I want f of the affine combination of those two X values is,
我想让这两个X的仿射组合的f值
at most, the affine combinations of the f's of those X values.
最大不超过它们的f(X)的仿射组合值
This is? It is the inductive hypothesis where n equals two.
就是说? 它又回归到n=2的时候归纳假设
Unfortunately, we didn't prove the n equals two case
悲剧了  我们还没证明n=2时的情况
is a special base case.
因为这是个特殊基础命题
So, we can't use induction here
所以这里不能用归纳法
the way that I've stated the base case.
因为我们给出的基础条件是n=1
If you did n equals two base case,
如果你证明了n=2的情况
you can do that. Here, we can't.
你就可以那么做 但这里我们不能
So, the other answer is by convexity, good.
所以第二个方法就是用 凹凸性 很好
That's right here.
就是这个式子
So, f is convex. We know that this is true for any two X values,
如果说f是个凹函数  对于任意两个X
and provided these two sum to one.
如果这两项的系数的和为1时 这条式就成立了
So, we know that this is true.
好吧 既然是成立的
Now is when we apply induction.
现在就是用归纳法的时候了
So, now we are going to manipulate this right term by induction.
那么 我们就对等号右边进行归纳
See, before we didn't necessarily know that
我们不需要知道
n was bigger than two.
n比2大
But, we know that n is bigger than n minus one.
但是,我们知道n是比n-1大的
That much, I can be sure of.
这我点我是能肯定的
So, this is one minus alpha n times the sum,
所以 这里是1-α_n乘以,
k equals one to n minus one of alpha k over one
α_k*f(x_k)/(1-α_n),k从1到n-1的总和
minus alpha n times f of x_k, if I got that right.
如果我没错的话
This is by induction, the induction hypothesis,
这里就可以用归纳法 归纳假设
because these alpha k's over one minus alpha n sum to one.
因为这α_k/(1-α_n)的总和为1
Now, these one minus alpha n's cancel,
然后 消掉1-αn
and we just get what we want.
我们就得到了我们想要的
This is sum k equals one to n of alpha k, f of x_k.
刚好就是α_k*f(x_k)的总和
So, we get f of the sum is, at most, sum of the f's.
所以我们推出把和的f值 最大不超过所有f值的和
That proves the lemma.
引理得证
OK, a bit tedious, but each step is pretty straightforward.
有点繁琐  但每一步都很明了
Do you agree?
你们觉得呢?
Now, it turns out to be
那现在 我们就应该
relatively straightforward to prove Jensen's inequality.
用它用来证明Jensen不等式
That's the magic.
下面是见证奇迹的时刻
And then, we get to do the expectation analysis.
我们要先做一下期望分析
So, we use our good friends, indicator random variables.
这里要用到我们的好朋友 指标随机变量
OK, but for now, we just want to prove this statement.
现在 我们想证明这个命题
If we have a convex function, f of the expectation is,
如果我们有个凹函数f  那f(E[X])
at most, expectation of f of that random variable.
就小于等于E[f(X)]
OK, this is a random variable, right?
这个是随机变量 是吧?
If you want to sample from this random variable,
比如你想对它采样
you sample from X, and then you apply f to it.
你就先从X采样  然后代入f中
That's the meaning of this notation, f of X
这就是这个符号的意义 f(X)
because X is a random variable.
因为X就是随机变量
We get to use that f is convex.
我们设f为一个凹函数
OK, it turns out this is not hard,
这个并不难
if you remember the definition of expectation,
如果还记得期望的定义的话
oh, I want to make one more assumption here,
对了 我想再做多一点假设
which is that X is integral.
假设X是整数值
So, it's an integer random variable,
那它就是一个整型随机变量
meaning it takes integer values.
这说明它是一个整型
OK, that's all we care about
这里也是要注意一下的
because we're looking at running times.
因为我们观察的是运行时间
This statement is true for continuous random variables, too,
虽然这个命题对于连续随机变量而言也是成立的
but I would like to do the discrete case
但我们研究的是离散的情况
because then I get to write down what U of X is.
要不然我还要写下X的域是多少
So, what is the definition of E of X?
那么  E[X]的定义是什么?
X only takes on integer values.
X只能取整数值
This is easy, but you have to remember it.
这很简单但是你们要记住它
It's a good drill.
这是道好题目
I don't really know much about X
我真的对X了解不多
except that it takes on integer values.
只知道它取整数值
Any suggestions on how I should expand the expectation of X?
有没人知道X的期望还告诉我们什么?
How many people know this by heart?
有多少人完全理解这个?
OK, it's not too easy then.
好吧  好像有点难
Well, expectation has something to do with probability, right?
期望这东西跟概率有关的 对吧?
So, I should be looking at something like the probability that
所以 从概率的角度上看
X equals some value, x.
当X等于某个值 它有个概率
That would seem like a good thing to do.
这是一个提示
What else goes here?
然后这里可以看成?
A sum, yeah.
一个和,对
The sum, well, X could be somewhere
一个和  嗯  X可以在
between minus infinity and infinity.
正负无穷之间取值
That's certainly true.
这是当然的
And, we have some more?
还有呢?
There's something missing here.
这里还少了点东西
What is this sum? What does it come out to
如果就这样看  它的和是多少？
for any random variable, X, that takes on integer values?
对于任意的整形随机变量来说？
One, good.
是1 很好
So, I need to add in something here, namely X.
所以 我还要在这里加上一个X
OK, that's the definition of the expectation.
这就是期望的定义
Now, f of a sum of things,
现在又是总和的f值
where these coefficients sum to one
而且这些系数的和又是1
looks an awful lot like the lemma that we just proved.
这就跟我们之前证明过的引理非常相像
OK, we proved it in the finite case.
我们已经在有限大的情况下证明了它
It turns out, it holds just as well if you take all integers.
但实际上 即使所有整数放进去它还是成立的
So, I'm just going to assume that.
好 我先假设是这样
So, I have these probabilities, these alpha values sum to one.
因为这些概率 也就是α 加起来等于1
Therefore, I can use this inequality,
所以  我可以用这个不等式
that this is, at most, let me get this right,
所以它小于或等于  让我整理下
I have the alphas, so I have a sum,
对应引理中的α  这里是Σ求和
x equals minus infinity to infinity of the alphas,
x从负无穷到正无穷
which are a probability;
α在这里就是概率
capital X equals little x times f of the value, f of little x.
概率Pr(X=x)乘以f(x)
OK, so there it is. I've used the lemma.
好的 就是这样 引理用过了
So, maybe now I'll erase the lemma.
现在可能我要把引理擦掉了
OK, I cheated by using the countable version
我偷懒只用引理的可数版本
of the lemma while only proving the finite case.
来证明有限的情况
It's all I can do in lecture.
但课堂上只能做这么多了
So, this is by a lemma.
那么 这些都是从引理推出的
Now, what I'd like to prove and leave some blank space here is
现在  我想证明的是  这里留点空白
this is, at most, E of f of X,
就是  最大为E[f(X)]
so that this summation is,
就是说这个和
at most, E of f of X.
最大为E[f(X)]
Actually, it's equal to E of f of X.
实际上它等于E[f(X)]
And, it really looks kind of equal, right?
看起来它们就是相等的  对吧？
You've got sum of some probabilities times f of X.
一些概率乘以f(X) 然后再求和
It almost looks like the definition of E of f of X, but it isn't.
看起来就像是E[f(X)]的定义  但其实它不是
You've got to be a little bit careful because E of f of X
这里要小心一点 因为E[f(X)]
should talk about the probability
其实是指关于
that f of X equals a particular value.
f(X)等于某个特定值时的概率
We can relate these as follows.
我们可以把它们列出来
It's not too hard.
不是很难
You can look at each value that f takes on,
这里的小x代表f所有的取值
and then look at all the values, k,
然后这里是所有
that map to that value, x.
满足f(k)=x的k值
So all the k's where f of X equals x,
k作为X的取值 使得f(X)=x的
the probability that X equals k,
X=k的概率
OK, this is another way of
好的 这是另外一种
writing the probability that f of X equals x.
用来表示f(X)=x的概率的写法
OK, so, in other words,
那么 也就是说
I'm grouping the terms in a particular way.
我在用一个特别的方法将这些项组合起来
I'm saying, well, f of X takes on various values.
我想说的是  f(X)有很多不同取值
Clever me to switch.
我又犯迷糊了
I used to use k's unannounced,
我老是用到k
so I better call this something else.
应该换一个叫法
Let's call this Y, sorry, switch notation here.
设它为y 不好意思 换个符号表示
It makes sense.
这样就好点了
I should look at the probability that X equals x.
我应该观察X=x时的概率
So, what I really care about is
那么  我真正关心的是
what this f of X value takes on.
f(X)到底能取什么值
Let's just call it Y,
我们设他为y
look at all the values, Y, that f could take on.
f能取到的所有的值 称为y
That's the range of f. And then,
其实就是f的值域  然后...
I'll look at all the different values of X where f of X equals Y.
我找出满足f(X)=y的所有X
If I add up those probabilities,
如果我把这些概率全加起来
because these are different values of X.
因为这些X都是不同的
Those are sort of independent events.
这都是一系列的独立事件
So, this summation will be the probability that f of X equals Y.
所以这个和就是f(X)=y的概率
This is capital X.
这个是大写X
This is little y. And then,
小写y 然后
if I multiply that by y, I'm getting the expectation of f of X.
如果我用y乘以它  就得到f(X)的期望
So, think about this, these two inequalities hold.
你们思考一下  这两个不等式
This may be a bit bizarre here
这里可能有点奇怪
because these sums are potentially infinite.
因为这些和可能是无穷大
But, it's true.
但它是成立的
OK, this proves Jensen's inequality.
好的 这样就证明了Jensen不等式
So, it wasn't very hard, just a couple of boards,
不是非常难  才写满了几块黑板
once we had this powerful convexity lemma.
一旦我们有了这个强大的凹性引理
So, we just used convexity.
那么,我们只需要利用凹性
We used the definition of E of X. We used convexity.
我们利用期望的定义 利用凹凸性质
That lets us put the f's inside.
它让我们将f代进去
Then we do this regrouping of terms, and we figure out,
然后再重组一下 就发现
oh, that's just E of f of X.
噢  这就是E[f(X)]了
So, the only inequality here is coming from convexity.
所以这个不等式是从凹性得来的
All right, now comes the algorithms.
好吧,现在回归到算法上
So, this was just some basic probability stuff,
刚说的这些都是基本的概率学的东西
which is good to practice.
很有实用性
OK, we could see in the quiz, which is not surprising.
好吧 课堂测验里面会有的 别惊讶
This is the case for me, too.
我也是这样过来的
You have a lot of intuition with algorithms.
你学算法时会有很多直观的想法
Whenever it's algorithmic, it makes a lot of sense
在算法的角度看 好像讲得通
because you're sort of grounded in some things that you know
因为你是在根据一些已知的知识来看问题的
because you are computer scientists, or something of that ilk.
因为你是个计算机学者 或是其它类似的
For the purposes of this class, you are computer scientists.
从这门课的目的来看  你们就是计算机学者
But, with sort of the basic probability,
但在概率学角度上看
unless you happen to be a mathematician, it's less intuitive,
除非你是个数学家  要不很难一眼看出来
and therefore harder to get fast.
因此也很难迅速解决问题
And, in quiz one, speed is pretty important.
测验一里  速度是很重要的
On the final, speed will also be important.
到期末测验  速度也很重要
The take home certainly doesn't hurt.
当然家庭作业影响不大
So, the take home is more interesting
所以作业更有趣点
because it requires being clever.
因为你得多用脑子
You have to actually be creative.
你得更具有创造力
And, that really tests algorithmic design.
而且 那是真正地在考验你的算法设计能力
So far, we've mainly tested analysis, and just,
到目前为止 我们主要考的是分析 比如,
can you work through probability?
你会用概率去证明吗?
Can you figure out what the,
你能想到...
can you remember what your running time
你能记得随机化的快速排序
of randomized quicksort is, and so on?
它的运行时间是多少？诸如此类
Quiz two will actually test creativity
测验二就会考大家创造力
because you have more time.
因为给你们的时间更多了
It's hard to be creative in two hours.
两个小时确实很难设计出什么
OK, so we want to analyze the expected height
好吧 那么我们想要分析一棵...
of a randomly constructed binary search tree.
随机构造的二叉搜索树的期望高度
So, I've defined this before,
虽然我之前已经定义过了
but let me repeat it
但我再重复一遍
because it was a while ago almost at the beginning of lecture.
因为已经过了一段时间了
I'm going to take the random variable
我们要用到一个随机变量
of the height of a randomly built binary search tree on n nodes.
来表示一棵随机化的n结点二叉树的高度
So, that was randomized, the n values.
它的n个元素都已经被随机化过了
Take a random permutation,
用随机的排列顺序
insert them one by one from left to right with tree insert.
从左到右一个个插入到树中
What is the height of the tree that you get?
这样的话 树的高度是多少?
What is the maximum depth of any node?
所有点的最大深度是多少?
I'm not going to look so much at X_n.
我不研究X_n本身
I'm going to look at the exponentiation of X_n.
我先看X_n的期望
And, still we have no intuition why.
我们仍然没什么直观的答案
But, two to the X is a convex function.
但是2的X次方就是一个凹函数
OK, it looks like that. It's very sharp.
好的  它看起来是这样的 非常陡
That's the best I can do for drawing, two to the X.
原谅我的渣画工吧 这其实是2的X次方
You saw how I drew my histogram.
其实我的柱状图更瞎眼
So, we want to somehow write this random variable
我们之所以要把它设成随机变量
as something, OK, in some algebra.
再写进这些代数式子里
The main thing here is to split into cases.
主要就是为了能够分情况讨论
That's how we usually go
我们通常都会这么做
because there's lots of different scenarios on what happens.
因为这会分成很多种不同的情况
So, I mean, how do we construct a tree from the beginning?
我的意思是 我们一开始怎么建立这棵树?
First thing we do is we take the first node.
第一件事是我们找第一个结点
We throw it in, make it the root.
加进树里 作为根
OK, so whatever the first value happens to be in the array,
好吧  所以不管数组的第一个数是什么
which we don't really know how that
我们并不关心这个数组...
falls into sorted order, we put it at the root.
它是什么样顺序 我们把它放在根的位置
And, it stays the root.
它就成了根结点
We never change the root from then on.
我们之后都不改变根结点
Now, of all the remaining elements,
现在 对于剩下的根结点
some of them are less than this value, and they go over here.
有些是小于这个点 它们就往这边走
So, let's call this r at the root.
我们设根结点为r吧
And, some of them are greater than r.
然后有另外一些是大于r的
So, they go over here.
就走到这里去了
Maybe there's more over here.
可能有些在这儿
Maybe there's more over here. Who knows?
可能有些在那儿 谁知道呢？
Arbitrary partition, in fact, uniformly random partition,
任意划分 实际上是均匀随机划分
which should sound familiar,
这样说你们可能更熟悉
whether there are k elements over here,
无论这边有k个元素
and n minus k minus one elements over here,
还是那边有n-k个元素
for any value of k, that's equally likely
k取任意值  都是等可能的
because this is chosen uniformly.
因为挑选k值的概率是均匀的
The root is chosen uniformly.
挑选根节点的概率也是均匀的
It's the first element in a random permutation.
它只是随机全排列的第一个元素
So, what I'm going to do is parameterize by that.
那么  我准备将这个参数化
How many elements are over here,
这里有多少个点
and how many elements are over here?
这里又有多少个点?
Because this thing is, again, a randomly built binary search tree
由于这棵树是 无论这里有多少结点
on however many nodes are in there
它都是随机二叉搜索树
because after I pick r,
那我选出了r之后
it's determined who is to the left and who is to the right.
哪些在左 哪些在右 就已经决定好了
And so, I can just partition.
所以 我只要划分就行了
It's like running quicksort.
就像快速排序过程一样
I partition the elements left of r, the elements right of r,
我把元素划分到r的左边 r的右边
and I'm sort of recursively constructing
然后我再递归地构建这棵树
a randomly built binary search tree on those two sub-permutations
再在树两边的子排列上 构建随机二叉搜索树
because sub-permutations of uniform permutations are uniform.
因为均匀打乱的全排列  它的子排列也是均匀打乱的
OK, so these are essentially recursive problems.
好吧 这本质上是递归的问题
And, we know how to analyze recursive problems.
我们知道怎么分析递归型的问题
All we need to know is that there are
我们只需要知道
k minus one elements over here,
这里有k-1个元素
and n minus k elements over here.
那里有n-k个元素
And, that would mean that r has rank k,
然后 这表示r排在第k位
remember, rank in the sense of the index in assorted order.
要记住 这个"第几位"就是指排序后的数组下标
So, where should I go?
那么 我们讲到哪了?
So, if the root, r, has rank, k,
如果这个根结点r排在第k位
so if this is a statement about condition on this event,
如果这是一次事件中的条件命题
which is a random event, then what we have is X_n equals
这事件是随机事件  那么我们就有X_n等于
one plus the max of X_(k minus one), X_(n minus k)
1加上X_k-1、X_n-k间的最大值
because the height of this tree is
因为整棵树的高度是
the max of the heights of the two subtrees plus one
两边子树的高度的最大值加一
because we have one more level up top.
最顶层也要算一层
OK, so that's the natural thing to do.
所以 自然会有这条式子
What we are trying to analyze, though, is Y_n. So, for Y_n,
我们要分析的是Y_n  所以对于Y_n
we have to take two to this power.
我们设它为2的X_n次方
So, it's two times the max of two to the X_(k minus one),
所以 它等于2乘以取最大值...2^X_k-1
which is Y_(k minus one),
也就是Yk-1
and two to this, which is Y_(n minus k).
然后是2^X_n-k,也就是Yn-k
And, now you start to see, maybe, why we are interested in Y's
也许你们已经开始明白 为什么我们对Y感兴趣
instead of X's in the sense that it's what we know how to do.
而不是对X  因为要这样 我们才知道怎么做
When we solve a recursion, when we solve,
当我们要处理递归问题时
like, the expected running time,
例如  运行时间的期望
we haven't taken expectations, yet, here.
我们这里还没求期望
But, when we compute the expected running time of quicksort,
但是 当我们计算快排的运行时间的期望时
we have something like two times, I mean,
我们也有像这样 用2乘以.. 我意思是
we have a couple of recursive subproblems,
我们会遇到一些递归的子问题
which are being added together.
它们会叠加起来
OK, here, we have a factor of two.
就比如这里  我们有个因子2
Here, we have a max.
这里有个最大值
But, intuitively, we know how to multiply random variables
但是 直观来讲 我们知道如何拿随机变量...
by a constant because that's, like,
去和一个常数相乘  就像
there's two recursive subproblems
这两个递归子问题
of the size is equal to the max of these two,
这个值等于这两个中的最大值
which we don't happen to know here.
虽然我们并不知道它是多少
But, there it is, whereas one plus,
但是 这里的话 由于是1加上某某
we don't know how to handle so well.
我们就不好处理了
And, indeed, our techniques
而实际上 我们是能够
are really good at solving recurrences,
很好地解决递归问题的
except up to the constant factors.
除非遇到有常数因子的情况
And, this one plus really doesn't affect
而且 这个1+看起来确实
the constant factor too much, it would seem.
不怎么会影响常数因子 似乎是这样
OK, but it's a big deal.
但它其实是有很大关系的
In exponentiation, it's a factor of two.
如果取幂的话 它就变成因子2
So here, it's really hard to see what this one plus is doing.
但这里 我们很难知道这个1+要怎么处理
And, our analysis, if we tried it,
如果我们真要尝试分析它的话
and it's a good idea to try it at home and see what happens,
你们自己在家里自己试试也是不错的
if you tried to do what I'm about to do with X_n,
如果你尝试从X_n入手分析
the one plus will sort of get lost, and you won't get a bound.
你可能会迷失在这个1+这里 然后就找不出头绪
You just can't prove anything.
什么都证明不了
With a factor of two, we're in good shape.
当我们用因子2  情况就好多了
We sort of know how to deal with that.
我们就大概明白怎么处理它了
We'll say more when we've actually done the proof
我们完成证明之后 我们再继续讨论
about why we use Y_n instead of X_n.
为什么这里要用Y_n来代替X_n
But for now, we're using Y_n.
但现在 我们要用Y_n
So, this is sort of a recursion,
那么 我们得到了一个递归方程
except it's conditioned on this event.
但它还是被限制在这个特定的事件里
So, how do I turn this into a statement that holds all the time?
那我们要怎么把递归转换成一个一般化的命题？
Sorry? Divide by the probability of the event?
抱歉 没听清？ 按照事件的概率来划分?
More or less. Indeed, these events are independent.
差不多  实际上 这些事件都是独立的
Or, they're all equally likely, I should say.
应该说 它们都是等可能事件
They're not independent.
它们并不是相互独立的
In fact, one determines all the others.
实际上 是决定一个影响全局的关系
So, how do I generally represent an event in algebra?
那么 怎么去用代数式来表达一次事件?
Indicator random variables: good.
指标随机变量  很好
Remember your friends, indicator random variables.
还记得指标随机变量吗?
All of these analyses use indicator random variables.
所有分析里都用了指标随机变量
So, they will just represent this event,
它们可以用来表示这一事件
and we'll call it Z_nk.
用Z_nk来表示
It's going to be one if the root has rank, k,
当根结点为第k位时 Z为1
and zero otherwise.
否则为0
So, in particular, the probability of,
所以 如果n是固定的
these things are all equally likely for,
你取任意的k值
a particular value of n if you try all the values of k.
对应事件发生的概率都会是相等的
The probability that this equals one,
Z_nk=1的概率
which is also the expectation of that indicator random variable,
等于这个指标随机变量的期望
which you should know, is it only takes values one or zero.
因为Z_nk不是为1就是为0
The zero doesn't matter in the expectation.
加上0并不影响期望的大小
So, this is going to be, hopefully,
所以这个很可能是
one over n if I got right.
1/n  如果我没错的话
So, there are n possibility
所以这里一共有
of what the rank of the root could be.
n种可能的根结点
Each of them are equally likely
而它们都是等概率的
because we have a uniform permutation.
因为排列是被均匀打乱的
So, now, I can rewrite this condition statement
现在我就可以重写这个命题
as a summation where the Z_nk's
写成Z_nk的形式
will let me choose what case I'm in.
那我就可以选择一种情况来讨论
So, we have Y_n is the sum, k equals one to n of Z_nk
所以Y_n等于Σ求和  k从1到n
times two times the max of X, sorry,
Z_nk 乘以2
Y, k minus one, Y_n minus k.
再乘以 Y_k-1、Y_n-k间的最大值
So, now we have our good friend, the recurrence.
现在 我们又看到老朋友——递归
We need to solve it.
我们要解开它
OK, we can't really solve it
其实并不是解递归
because this is a random variable,
因为这是一个随机变量
and it's talking about recursive random variables.
它还是个递推的随机变量
So, we first take the expectation of both sides.
那么 我们首先对两边取期望
That's the only thing we can really bound.
我们唯一能找到限界的东西
Y_n could be n^2 in an unlucky case, sorry, not n^2.
Y_n在坏情况下可能等于n^2  抱歉 不是n^2
It could be n^2.
它能等于n^2
It could be two to the, boy, two to the n if you are unlucky
但在更差的情况时它能等于2~n
because X_n could be as big as n, the height of the tree.
因为树的高度X_n可能等于n
And, Y_n is two to that.
而且  Y_n等于2的X_n次方
So, it could be two to the n.
所以 它可能是2的n次方
What we want to prove is that it's polynomial in n.
我们只想证明它的多项式阶为n
If it's n to some constant,
如果多项式只有n和常数时
and we take logs, it'll be order log n.
我们对它取对数 它就等于log n了
OK, so we'll take the expectation,
好吧  那我们来计算期望
and hopefully that will guarantee that this holds.
很明显这个是成立的
OK, so we have expectation of this summation
好的 指数随机变量乘以
of random variables times recursive random variables.
递归随机变量 它们加起来总和的期望
So, what is the first, woops, I forgot a bracket.
那么 首先 哎呀  漏了一个括号
What is the first thing that we do in this analysis?
我们在这个分析中要做的第一件事是什么?
This should, yeah, linearity of expectation.
这个应该 是的 期望的线性性质
That one's easy to remember.
这点很容易记住
OK, we have a sum. So, let's put the E inside.
好的 我们有一个和 那我们把E放进去
OK, now we have the expectation of our product.
好的 我们现在有个乘积的期望
What should we use? Independence.
有什么用? 独立性
Hopefully, things are independent.
显然 这些事件是相互独立
And then, we could write this.
然后 我们可以这样写
Then, it would be the expectation of the product.
它就等于两个期望的乘积
And, heck, let's put the two outside,
然后  我们把这个2放到外面
because it's not, no sense in keeping it in here.
因为它不是...把它留在这里没用
Y is there starting to look like X's?
Y是不是写得跟X有点像?
I can't even read them. Sorry about that.
我都差点认不出来了 不好意思
This should all be Y's.
这些应该全都是关于Y的
OK, very wise, random variables.
好的 很聪明 随机变量
So. Why are these independent?
那为什么它们是相互独立的?
So, here we are looking at the choice of what the root is,
这里我们关注的是根结点是哪个
what rank the root has in a problem of size n.
在有n个结点时 根结点排第几位
In here, we're looking at what the root, I mean,
在这里  我们关心根结点是什么 我的意思是
there are various choices of what the search tree
它可能会导致各种各样的情况
looks like in the stuff left of the root,
左边的树会是什么样子
and in the stuff right of the root.
右边的树会是什么样子
Those are independent choices
每种情况都是独立的
because everything is uniform here.
因为这些数都是均匀打乱的
So, the choice of this guy was uniform.
所以 挑选这家伙的概率是均匀的
And then, that determines
然后 这家伙也决定了
who partitions in the left and the right.
左边和右边又会选哪些点来做划分点
Those are completely independent recursive choices
它们都是相互独立的递归的选择
of who's the root in the left subtree?
比如哪个点会成为左子树的根?
Who's the root in the left of the left subtree, and so on?
哪个点又会是左子树的左子树的根  诸如此类
So, this is a little trickier than usual.
所以这里就更讲技巧
Before, it was random choices in the algorithm.
之前说它是算法里的随机选择的结果
Now, it's in some construction
现在说它在前面的随机数出来时
where we choose the random numbers ahead of time.
就已经被决定好了
It's a bit funny, but this is still independent.
虽然有点奇怪  但它仍然是独立的
So, we get this just like we did in quicksort, and so on.
这个过程就跟快速排序里的一样
OK. Now, we continue.
好的  我们继续
And, now it's time to be a bit sloppy.
接着  可能会讲得粗糙一点
Well, one of these things we know.
有一件事我们是知道的
OK, E of ZNK, that, we wrote over here.
E[Z_nk],写在这里的
It's one over n. So, that's cool.
等于1/n  太好了
So, we get a two over n outside,
那我们外面就变成2/n了
and we get this sum of the expectation
那我们这里就变成
of a max of these two things.
两者最大值的期望的总和
Normally, we would write, well,
通常  我们写成
I think sometimes you write T of max,
我想大家Tmax
or Y of the max of the two things here.
或者用Ymax来表示的
You've got to write it as the max of these two variables.
总之你得用两者中较大那个来表示
And, the trick, I mean, it's not too much of a trick,
然后 还有个小技巧  技巧从来不嫌多
is that the max is, at most, the sum.
技巧是两者的最大值不超过它们的和
So, we have nonnegative things.
因为它们是非负的
So, we have two over n, sum k equals one to n
那么 我们还有2/n  对k从1到n求和
of the expectation of the sum instead of the max.
然后这里变为和的期望 而不是最大值的期望
OK, this is, in some sense, the key step
好的 这个是关键步骤
where we are losing something in our bound.
我们开始把我们的限界放大了
So far, we've been exact.
在此之前  我们的限界都是精确的
Now, we're being pretty sloppy.
现在 我们开始变得宽松了
It's true the max is, at most, the sum.
的确  两者的最大值不超过它们的和
But, it's a pretty loose upper bound as things go.
但是 它是一个很宽松的上界
We'll keep that in mind for later.
这个我们先记住
What else can we do with the summation?
求和有什么用?
This should, again, look familiar.
这点看起来又挺熟悉的
Now that we have a sum of a sum of two things,
现在我们有两样东西的和的总和
I'm trying to like it to be a sum of one thing.
我想让它成为一样东西的和
Sorry? You can use linearity of expectation, good.
大声点? 可以利用期望的线性性质 好的
So, that's the first thing I should do.
我们要做的事第一件事是这个
So, linearity of expectation lets me separate that.
根据线性将它们分离出来
Now I have a sum of 2n things.
现在我有2个n项的和
Right, I could break that into the sum of these guys,
对 我可以将它分成这一部分的和
and the sum of these guys.
和那一部分的和
Do you know anything about those two sums?
关于这两个和你知道什么?
Do we know anything about those two sums?
我们已经知道什么?
They're the same. In fact,
它们实际上是相等的
every term here is appearing exactly twice.
每一项在这里都出现了两遍
One says a k minus one.
一个是k-1
One says an n minus k,
另一个是n-k
and that even works if it's odd, I think.
就算是奇数也是这样
So, in fact, we can just take one of the sums
那么 我们只需要算出其中一个和
and multiply it by two.
再用它乘以2
So, this is four over n times the sum,
所以这里是4/n乘以这个和
and I'll rewrite it a little bit
我在重新写一遍
from zero to n minus one of E of Y_k.
对E[Y_k]求和  k从0到n-1
Just check the number of times each Y_k
要知道每个Y_k
appears from zero up to n minus one is exactly two.
的出现次数刚好等于2
So, now I have a recurrence.
那我们现在有了这个递归
I have E of Y_n is, at most, this thing.
我推出了E[Y_n]最大等于这东西
Let's just write that for our memory.
这么写方便记忆
So, how's that? Cool.
如何? 很给力吧？
Now, I just have to solve the recurrence.
现在 我只需要解这个递归
How should I solve an ugly, hairy, recurrence like this?
我要怎么解开这个恶心的递归?
Substitution: yea! Not the master method.
代换法 嗯嗯 不是主方法
OK, it's a pretty nasty recurrence.
它是个相当恶心的递归
So, I'm going to make a guess,
我准备要猜一个数
and I've already told you the guess, that it's n^3.
而我已经告诉过你们  我猜的是n^3
I think n^3 is pretty much exactly
我觉得n^3相当准了
where this proof will be obtainable.
而且这个是能证明出来的
So, substitution method, substitution method
代换法 代换法
is just a proof by induction.
其实就是归纳法
And, there are two things every proof by induction should have,
所有归纳法都要求有两样东西
well, almost every proof by induction, unless you're being fancy.
基本上每个都是  除非你这么有想象力
It should have a base case,
它要求有一个基础命题
and the base case here is n equals order one.
这里的基础命题就是n为O(1)阶
I didn't write it, but, of course,
我没写出来 不过这是肯定的
if you have a constant size tree, it has constant height.
当你有常数级大小的树时  它的高度也是常数级的
So, this thing will be true
所以这是成立的
as long as we set true if c is sufficiently large.
只要我们设c充分大就为真
OK, so, don't forget that.
好的 别忘了基础命题
A lot of people forgot it on the quiz.
很多人考试的时候忘了这个
We even mentioned the base case.
我们有时甚至在出题时提及了基础命题
Usually, we don't even mention the base case.
虽然 通常我们并不提及基础命题
And, you should assume that there's one there.
但你应该假设有这么一个存在
And, you have to say this in any proof by substitution.
在使用代换法证明时 你就必须这么做
OK, now, we have the induction step.
好的 现在我们进行归纳
So, I claim that E of Y_n is, at most, C of n^3,
我要证明E[Yn]最大为C(n^3)
assuming that it's true for smaller n.
同时假设 对较小的n它也成立
You should write the induction hypothesis here,
你应该把归纳假设写这里
but I'm going to skip it because I'm running out of time.
但是我不写因为时间不够了
Now, we have this recurrence
我们有这个递推式
that E of Y_n is, at most, this thing.
E[Yn]最大等于 这东西
So, E of Y_n is, at most, four over n,
所以E[Yn]最大等于4/n
sum k equals zero to n minus one of E of Y_k.
乘以ΣE[Yk] k从0到n-1
Now, notice that k is always smaller than n.
我们注意到k总是比n小的
So, we can apply induction.
所以我们用上归纳
So, this is, at most, four over n,
这就是 最大为 4/n
sum k equals zero to n minus one of c times k^3.
乘以Σck^3   k从0到n-1
That's the induction hypothesis.
这个就是归纳假设
Cool. Now, I need an upper bound on this sum,
很好 现在 需要给这个和找到上界
if you have a good memory,
如果你记性好的话
then you know a closed form for this sum.
那你会知道一个接近这个和的式子
But, I don't have such a good memory as I used to.
但我没这么好记性
I never memorized this sum when I was a kid,
但我从来没记过这个和
so I don't remember everything
我都不记得
when I memorize when I was less than 12 years old.
12岁以前学过的东西都忘了
I still remember all the digits of pi, whatever.
不过我仍然记得圆周率
But, anything I try to memorize now
但是我现在想记住的东西
just doesn't quite stick the same way.
都没以前记得牢了
So, I don't happen to know this sum.
所以我认不出这个和
What's a good way to approximate this sum?
有什么好的方法去估算这个和吗?
Integral: good.
积分 很好
So, in fact, I'm going to take the c outside.
那么,我准备将c提出来
So, this is 4c over n.
这就变成4c/n
The sum is, at most, the integral.
这个和最大等于这个积分
If you get the range right, so, you have to go one larger.
如果把范围写的正确一点  你还得加上1
Instead of n minus one, you go up to n.
不是n-1  要把它加到n
This is in the textbook.
书上面有的
It's intuitive, too, as long as you have a monotone function. That's key
这又是直观的东西  只要说你有一个单调函数 这是关键
So, you have something that's like this.
这样的话  你就有一个这样的曲线
And, you know, the sum is taking each of these
然后 和就是将每个函数值都
and weighting them with a value of one.
按1加权相加得到的
The integral is computing the area under this curve.
积分就是计算弧线下面的面积
So, in particular, if you look at
所以  如果你观察
this approximation of the integral,
这个积分的逼近
then, I mean, this thing is certainly,
我的意思是 这东西就肯定是...
this would be the sum if you go one larger at the end,
当积分范围往后加1后 它就是那个和
and that's, at most, the integral.
那它就是最大为 这个积分
So, that's proof by picture.
那这就是这幅图的证明
But, you can see this in the book.
书上面有写
You should know it from 042 I guess.
第42面 好象是
Now, integrals, hopefully, you can solve.
现在 很容易就能算出这个积分
Integral of x^3 is x^4 over four.
x^3的积分等于x^4/4
I got it right. And then, we're valuing that at n.
我写对了  然后,将n代进去
And, it's zero. Subtracting the zero doesn't matter
这个是0 减去0不影响
because zero to the fourth power is zero.
0的四次方还是0
So, it's just n^4 over four.
所以它是n^4/4
So, this is 4c over n times n^4 over four.
所以有4c/n乘以n^4/4
And, conveniently, this four cancels with this four.
刚刚好,4跟4约掉
The four turns into a three because of this,
这个4要变成3  因为这里消掉了
and we get n^3.
然后有n^3
We get cn^3. Damn convenient,
我们得到cn^3 很顺利啊
because that's what we wanted to prove.
因为这正是我们想证明的
OK, so this proof is just barely snaking by: no residual term.
好的 只是这个证明稍微绕了下弯  因为它没有残余项
We've been sloppy all over the place,
这过程都很粗糙
and yet we were really lucky.
但我们运气真的好
And, we were just sloppy in the right places.
我们在适当的地方粗糙了点
So, this is a very tricky proof.
所以这个证明也要有点技巧的
If you just tried to do it by hand,
如果你自己试着做的话
it's pretty easy to be too sloppy,
很容易写得过分粗糙
and not get quite the right answer.
这样就变得不容易得到正确结果
But, this just barely works.
但这个就是恰好有用
So, let me say a couple of things about it
关于它的话 我想多说一点
in my remaining one minute.
还剩一分钟
So, we can do the conclusion, again.
那么我们又得出新结论
I won't write it because I don't have time,
没时间就不写了
but here it is. We just proved a bound on Y_n,
但是这里 我们刚刚证明Y_n的一个界限
which was two to the power X_n.
Y_n是2的X_n次方
What we cared about was X_n.
但我们关心的是X_n
So, we used Jensen's inequality.
那我们用Jensen不等式
We get the two to the E of X_n is, at most, E of two to the X_n.
我们有2的E[X_n]次方小于等于2的X_n次方的期望值
This is what we know about because that's Y_n.
这里就用上Y_n的定义
So, we know E of Y_n is now order n^3.
那现在我们知道E[Y_n]是O(n^3)
OK, we had to set this constant
好 我们设这个常数
sufficiently large for the base case.
是充分大的
We didn't really figure out what the constant was here.
我们没有不知道这个常数有多大
It didn't matter because now we're taking the logs of both sides.
但这不影响  因为我们要对两边取对数
We get E of X_n is, at most, log of order n^3.
我们得E[X_n]最大等于log O(n^3)
This constant is a multiplicative constant.
这个常数是乘上去的
So, you take the logs. It becomes additive.
所以 它在取对数时就成了加法的
This constant is an exponent.
这个常数是指数
So, it would take logs. It becomes a multiple.
取对数后变成乘数
Three log n plus order one.
3logn加上O(1)
This is a pretty damn tight bound on the height
这就是随机二叉搜索树高度
of a randomly built binary search tree,
的一个很紧凑的一个上界
the expected height, I should say.
期望高度 应该这么说
In fact, the expected height of X_n
实际上X_n的期望高度
is equal to, well, roughly, I'll just say it's roughly,
等于 我是说大约等于
I don't want to be too precise here, 2.9882 times log n.
我这里没法太精确 2.9882乘以log n
This is the result by a friend of mine,
这个是我的一个朋友算出来的
Luke Devroy, if I spell it right, in 1986.
Luke Devroy 1986年的时候
He's a professor at McGill University in Montreal.
他现在在McGill大学当教授
So, we're pretty close, three to 2.98.
不过我们已经算得很接近了  3对2.98
And, I won't prove this here.
我在这里不证了
The hard part here is actually the lower bound,
最难的部分是计算下界
but it's only that much.
不过就这么多吧
I should say a little bit more about
我应该再说说
why we use Y_n instead of X_n.
为什么用Y_n替换X_n
And, it's all about the sloppiness.
其实是马虎了
And, in particular, this step, where we said that
这一步 我们说
the max of these two random variables is, at most, the sum.
这两个数的最大值不超过它们的和
And, while that's true for X just
这个对于X成立
as well as it is true for Y, it's more true for Y.
对于Y也是成立的 但对Y更合适
OK, this is a bit weird because, remember,
这里有点奇怪 因为
what we're analyzing here is all possible values of k.
我们在这讨论的是k的所有可能的值
This has to work no matter what k is, in some sense.
因为这必须对于所有k值都成立
I mean, we're bounding all of those cases simultaneously,
我意思是 我们同一时间在估算所有这些情况的上下界
the sum of them all.
所有的情况
So, here we're looking at k minus one versus n minus k.
这里我们比较k-1和n-k
And, in fact, here, there's a polynomial version.
实际上 在这里 它是一个多项式的版本
But, so, if you take two values a and b, and you say,
但是 如果你取两个数a和b
well, max of ab is, at most, a plus b.
你可以说 a、b的最大值是小于等于a+b
And, on the other hand you say, well,
另一方面
max of two to the a and two to the b is,
2的a次方和2的b次方的最大值是
at most, two to the a plus two to the b.
小于等于2^a+2^b
Doesn't this feel better than that?
这个是不是比那个好理解
Well, they are, of course, the same.
当然两种都是一样的
But, if you look at a minus b, as that grows,
但当|a-b|逐渐变大时
this becomes a tighter bound faster
这一个收敛的速度
than this becomes a tighter bound
比那个收敛的速度要快
because here we're looking at
因为我们从...
absolute difference between a minus b.
a、b间的差距的绝对值来看的
So, that's why this is pretty good and this is pretty bad.
这就是为什么这个比那个更好
We're still really bad if a and b are almost the same.
即使a和b差不多大  它表现还是会很糟糕
But, we're trying to solve this
但是我们还是试着去解决这个问题
for all partitions into k minus one and n minus k.
对于所有k-1和n-k的可能的划分来说
So, it's OK if we get a few of the cases wrong
所以 尽管有些情况下是错的
in the middle where it evenly partitions.
例如它是刚好中分的时候 两边子树相等
But, as soon as we get some skew,
但是当倾斜得比较多的时候
this will be very close to this,
这个就非常接近这个了
whereas this will be still pretty far from this.
然而这个离这个还是很远
You have to get pretty close to the edge
那你就要在它放大的太多之前
before you're not losing much here,
迅速达到你想要的边界了
whereas pretty quickly you're not losing much here.
但是因为这里收敛速度很快  所以你不会放得太大
That's the intuition.
这只是直观的解释
Try it, and see what happens with X_n,
你们试下 看看X_n会怎样
and it won't work.
它解不出来
See you Wednesday.
星期三见